Finding Aid for Richard S. M. Emrich Papers 1940s-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard S. M. Emrich Papers 1940s-1990
Emrich, Richard S. M. (Richard Stanley Merrill), 1910-
6 linear feet
Episcopal bishop of Michigan. Scrapbooks and notebooks containing newspaper clippings; photographs relating to his church career, clippings of newspaper columns containing his views on current events, and copies of addresses and sermons.
851214 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Bishop Emrich (donor no. 4559 ) began donating his papers to the library in 1967. Periodic additions from Bishop Emrich and from the Diocese of Michigan have been made since then.
The collection is open for research.
Richard Stanley Merrill Emrich was born March 11, 1910 in Mardin, Turkey. His father was a Congregational missionary who was stationed there at the time. Emrich spent his boyhood in Framingham, Massachusetts and received his Bachelor's degree from Brown University in 1932. In 1935, he received his Bachelor of Divinity degree from Union Theological Seminary and from there went to Marburg University in Germany to earn his Ph.D. in 1938.
After his ordination in Boston, Emrich spent a brief time as a parish curate and then spent the next ten years teaching at the Episcopal Theological Seminary in Cambridge, Massachusetts, where he achieved the rank of full professor.
On June 11, 1946, Emrich was consecrated as Suffragan Bishop of Michigan at the age of thirty-six. Two years later, he became the seventh Bishop of Michigan, the youngest Episcopalian bishop ever in a Michigan diocese. He held this position for twenty-seven years, one of the longest terms for the Michigan diocese. In his retirement, Emrich and his wife, Beatrice, moved to Sun City, Arizona, where he continues to assist others.
During his long career, Emrich was not only involved with official church business, but also was very active in local and world affairs. He was a major supporter of the civil rights movement, as well as a supporter for social justice and arbitrator in union-management disputes. He wrote a weekly Sunday column for The Detroit News as well as a daily question and answer column. Over the years, Emrich was awarded eight honorary degrees, and in 1958 was also awarded the CBE - Honorary Commander of the Civil Division of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire - by Queen Elizabeth II for his efforts in promoting Anglo-American relations.
The materials in this collection chronicle Emrich's career as Episcopal Bishop of Michigan. The collection contains correspondence, sermons and speeches given by Emrich and published material. The Collection has been divided into the following series: Subject Files; Visual Materials; Writings, sermons, and addresses; Scrapbooks; and Sound Recording.
Subjects:
Clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; Emrich, Richard S. M. (Richard Stanley Merrill), 1910-; Episcopal Church.; Episcopal Church--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Anglican churches.; Church schools--Michigan.; Churches.; Clergymen.; Emrich family.; Emrich, Richard S. M. (Richard Stanley Merrill), 1910-; Episcopal Church. Diocese of Michigan.; Japan.; Religious services.
Genre/Form:
DVDs.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Subject files
  - Awards, citations, and personal (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Lambeth Conference (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Column
    - undated (Box 1)
    - 1974-1979, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Pastoral letters (Box 1)
  - Report from the Bishop, European Tour 1962 (Box 1)
  - West Branch Trinity Church 1946, 1968 (Box 1)
- Visual Materials
  Visual materials includes portraits, photos taken at various meetings and church functions; and photos of miscellaneous Episcopal church buildings in the Michigan diocese; also motion picture film of Bishop Emrich made at WWJ-TV, Detroit, September 22, 1961. Emrich discusses a variety of contemporary issues including civil rights, "freedom riders" and the role of the church in society.
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Michigan P. E. Churches (Box 1)
  - Motion picture
    - Bishop Emrich on WWJ-TV September 22, 1961, 851214-1
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, optical, 00:59:48
        [Restricted]
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 851214-1, flv
- Writings, sermons, and addresses
  The Writings, sermons, and addresses series is largely arranged chronologically and contains speeches that Emrich made while Bishop of Michigan. The occasion for these speeches were varied and were often given to groups outside of the church, although the majority of them have a religious theme. Also in this series are a set of addresses pertaining to civil rights as well as a copy of his Reinecker Lectures (an annual lecture series of the Theological Seminary of Alexandria, Virginia) of 1951. The sermons were preached by Emrich on different occasions. Many of these sermons were for ordination ceremonies and holidays.
  - Articles and Commentaries 1950s-1960s (Box 6)
  - Journal 1951 (Box 6)
  - Lectures, Addresses, and Sermons
    - Lectures and Addresses
      - Undated (Box 6)
      - 1951-1971, 5 folders (Box 6)
      - Civil Rights 1957 (Box 6)
      - Reinecker Lectures 1951 (Box 6)
      - Addresses, various dates (Box 6)
    - Sermons
      - undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 1949-1990, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Pamphlets, 2 expandable folders (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks
  - Newspaper Column 1968-1970, 8 volumes (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Column 1971-1973, 8 volumes (Box 3)
  - General career and newspaper column 1957-1967, 8 volumes (Box 4)
  - Gift of Osaka, Japan, Diocese 1951 (Box 5)
  - Gift of All Saints of Brooklyn, Michigan 1966 (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Column 1967 and other (Box 5)
  - Personal 1946-1951, 3 folders; 1 volume (Box 5)
    contain numerous photographs
- Sound recording
  - Cassette sound tape of oral interview 1984, 60 minutes; 1 audio-cassette (Box 5)